<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle both of Godly consolacion and also of aduertisement written by Iohn Caluine the pastour &amp; preacher of Geneua, to the right noble prince Edvvarde Duke of Somerset, before the tyme or knoweledge had of his trouble, but delyuered to the sayde Duke, in the time of his trouble, and so translated out of frenshe by the same Duke.</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17651</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118174</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853383</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18766</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17651)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18766)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 877:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle both of Godly consolacion and also of aduertisement written by Iohn Caluine the pastour &amp; preacher of Geneua, to the right noble prince Edvvarde Duke of Somerset, before the tyme or knoweledge had of his trouble, but delyuered to the sayde Duke, in the time of his trouble, and so translated out of frenshe by the same Duke.</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
                  <author>Somerset, Edward Seymour, Duke of, 1506?-1552.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [W. Baldwin? in the shop of] Edward Whitchurche,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the .v. daye of Aprill. 1550]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; actual printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Somerset, Edward Seymour, --  Duke of, 1506?-1552 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18766:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18766:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An epiſtle both of GoDLy Conſolacion and alſo of aduertiſement, written by Iohn Caluine the paſtour &amp; preacher of Geneua, to the right noble prince EDvvarde Duke of Somerſet, before the tyme or knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge had of his trouble, but delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſayde Duke, in the time of his trouble, and ſo tranſlated out of frenſhe by the ſame Duke.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18766:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18766:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat nothing is more odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or deteſtable afore god then the diſobedience of ſubiectes againſt their Kynges and Gouernours, maye partly by moſte open teſtimonies of holy Scripture euydentlye appeare, and partly by thys argument be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly proued, that it hath neuer yet vnto thys daye, neyther in goddes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected people the Iſraelytes, nor yet in anye other common weale, eyther Heathen or Chriſtyan, eſcaped with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out moſte grieuous plages and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Yet neuertheles ſo merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a god he is, of ſo long ſufferance, ſo lothe to ſtryke, and ſo deſyrous of mans amendment: that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his diuyne maieſtie, ere he will take extreme vengeaunce for tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous dyſobedyence of the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte theyr heades, to geue manye ſondrye kyndes of warnynges for vs to beware by. Firſt he hath nowe in theſe laſt daies, reyſed vp many god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preachers, who ceaſe not daylye to
<pb facs="tcp:18766:3"/> publiſh (as it were) gods proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion in thys behalfe, plainely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng to all eſtates and degrees, what theyr duety is. He hath prouided ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny godly exhortacions and treatyſes dayly to come forth to the ſame effect &amp; purpoſe. Yea, and leſte any manne ſhould thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he will daly in ſuche a matter, he made vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt Soomer here in England to feele a littel touch of his ſharpe rod, by the kinges regal ſworde, beyng a moſt euydent token of hys great wrath and indignacy on agaynſte all Rebelles, and ſedicious murmurers. God hath of his infinite goodnes not only made litle Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſtrong enoughe to withſtand al forein puiſſaunce, (yf we holde togethers, and agree well emonges our ſelues, obeying the king and magiſtrates as we ought to dooe:) but alſo by many vndoubtable tokens hathe declared that he myndeth (as it were) to make hys habytacyon and dwellyng place here emong vs, of purpoſe to be our ſure defence and proteccion, yf we wil
<pb facs="tcp:18766:3"/> receiue him accordyngly. But in caſe we wilbe ſo hard herted, as wilfully to refuſe the grace of his goſpell moſt mercyfully and moſt fatherly offered vnto vs: it cannot bee doubted ne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded, but that thextreme plages of gods wrath and vengeaunce will at length lyght vpon all ſuch as eyther of an vngodly hearte will ſwell and ſtryue agaynſt the grace and trueth of hys woorde, which he hath ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges vs: or els of a malicious fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes wil repine, and murmure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt theyr heades &amp; rulers. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou haſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here ſet furth vnto the, good Chriſtian reader, an Epiſtle of Iohn Caluyne, written in frenche vnto the ryght noble prynce Edward Duke of Somerſet, and ſent hither into Englande immediately vpon the late commocion here in thys realme. And by thys Epiſtle it maye to the godly reader very wel appeare, how tenderly god of hys goodnes dooeth embrace vs, and doeth (as it were) ſet vs in hys owne lappe, myndyng to
<pb facs="tcp:18766:4"/> kepe vs ſafe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al perils of outward enemies, vnder the ſhadowe and ſure defence of his own winges. He decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelf ſo mercifully to prouide for vs, (if we will gladlye and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglye receyue hys grace, and ſtande therein) that he maketh them care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for vs that neuer wer in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, nor neuer had to doe with vs, ſauing onely that (as the nature and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of chriſtian charitie is) they wiſhe and daylye praye, that we maye haue grace ſo to vſe oure ſelues, that the bleſſing of god which he hath ſo ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſlye powred vpon vs, maye not through our vnthankefulnes bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away agayne: whiche foraſmuch as it ſo is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let not vs be leſſe carefull for our ſelues, than other ſtraungers be. Let vs not haue receiued the grace of God in vayne. Let vs ſtand in the trueth, and cleaue to Chriſtes goſpel, and by the ſame, lette vs practiſe (as it teacheth vs) to obeye quietely and willingly our rulers and gouernours by him appointed. Which it we do, he
<pb facs="tcp:18766:4"/> wil ſo defende vs with his almighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful arme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al foreyne enemies (what euer they be) ſhal eyther bee vnhable to doe vs any ſcathe: or els ſhall be turned in theyr heartes, and of eager enemies ſhall beecome oure earneſt frendes and folowers. Whiche thinge GOD graunte.</p>
            <p>To whome be all honor and prayſe, worlde without end.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18766:5"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle of John Caluine</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y lord, although god hath geuen vnto you ſyngu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitye, and other vertues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to the place wherein he hath ordeyned you, and in thaffayres that he hath put in your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des: Yet neuertheles, foraſmuche as ye dooe eſteme me for a ſeruante of his ſonne (whome aboue al ye deſyre to obeye,) I am certen that for the loue of him, you wil gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receyue that, which I write vnto you in hys name: as in dede I pretende no other end, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in folowyng that, that you haue begonne, you might more and more aduaunce his
<pb facs="tcp:18766:5"/> honoure, vnto the tyme that you ſhal haue eſtabliſhed his reigne in ſuche perfeccion, as it may be knowen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. And alſo you ſhal know, that withoute aduauncyng anye thing of myne owne fantaſy, al that I write ſhalbe drawen oute of hys pure doctryne. If I conſidered not other cauſes then the dignitie and greate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes where ye be: there wer no meane for a man of my quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye to wryte vnto you. But foraſmuche as you refuſe not to be taught of the maſter, the whiche I ſerue: but that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you preferre to al the reſt the grace that he hath geuen vnto you, to be one of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: I thynke that I haue
<pb facs="tcp:18766:6"/> no nede to make vnto you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny long excuſe or preface, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I fynd you ſufficiently dyſpoſed to receyue all that ſhall proceede of hym. We haue all to render thankes vnto our Lorde GOD and father, in that he will be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of you in ſo excellente a woorke, as in ſettyng foorthe agayne (by youre meanes,) the pure and true rule of hys ſeruyce in Englande: and in cauſing the doctrine of health to haue place, and to be there faythefullye publyſſhed, for all them that will heare the ſame. And for that as he hath geuen vnto you ſuche vertue and conſtancye to purſue it vnto this time againſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:18766:6"/> temptacions and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: And for that alſo that he hathe ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghtned you in bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge all youre deuyſes and laboures, for the proſperyng of them, they be thynges that ſtyrreth all true faythefull menne to magnify his name. But in the meane tyme, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that Sathan ceaſſeth not to rayſe vp by all wayes, newe combates,<note place="margin">There is nothynge more hard then to cauſe the woorde of god peaceablye to rewle e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people.</note> and that it is a thynge of it ſelfe ſo hard as there canne bee nothynge more harde then to cauſe the woorde of GOD peaceablye to rewle emonges the people (the whiche of theyr nature are geuen to lyes:) And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuche as there be ſo many cyrcumſtances which in theſe
<pb facs="tcp:18766:7"/> dayes empeache the courſe of the ſame, and aboue all, that the ſuperſticions of the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte hauyng taken roote of ſo long tyme, may not eaſely bee taken awaye from theyr heartes: Me thynketh you haue great nede to be confyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by holye exhortacyons. And I doubt not, but that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teacheth you to feele the ſame, whiche ſhall bee the cauſe to make me to procede the more frankelye, beecauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my purpoſe (as I belieue) ſhalbe conformable to youre deſyre. And albeit that my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortacions ſhall bee ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: yet I am ſure that you wil beare with the good zeale and affeccion, that ſtirreth me
<pb facs="tcp:18766:7"/> to doe it. Wherfore according to reaſon, I belieue that the neceſſitie which ye feele, ſhall cauſe that the ſame ſhalbee a greate deale the better recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: Howeſoeuer it ſhalbee, I beſeche you my lorde, that it may pleaſe you to geue me the hearynge in ſome aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes which I entend brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to declare vnto you, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng that when ye ſhall haue hearde it, at the leaſt you ſhal fynde ſome ſauor for to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforted, and to take a great deale the better courage to continue the holye and noble enterpriſe, in the whiche god hath appointed you to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed vnto this preſent.</p>
            <p>I doubte not but the greate
<pb facs="tcp:18766:8"/> troubles whyche happened vnto you not long agoe, haue beene vnto you verye harde and annoyouſe: and moſte of all for that manye myghte haue taken occaſion of ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre, for aſmuche as they were moued (in ſome parte) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadowe of chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng the Religyon. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it cannot bee but that it hathe beene vnto you a verye harde aſſaulte, aſwell for the cares, whiche myghte come vnto you, as alſo for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the malygners and Ignorauntes, and alſo for the feare and trouble of the good. Truelye the brute that I haue heard a farre of, hath cauſed me to haue great grief
<pb facs="tcp:18766:8"/> in my hearte, vnto ſuche time that I dyd knowe that God had begonne to put ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. Neuertheles, for that, that they be not yet al pacify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that the deuill may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe them agayne: you ſhall call to remembraunce that, that the holy ſtory recyteth of the good king Ezechias: that is to ſaye, at ſuche tyme as he hadde abolyſhed the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticyons in Iewerye,<note place="margin">Ezechias at his fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> reforinyng of the church was fore op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed of enemies</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the ſtate of the church according to the law of god, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was ſo oppreſſed of his enemies, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was very lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to be a loſte and deſperate manne. It is not withoute cauſe that the holye Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte notablye expreſſeth that
<pb facs="tcp:18766:9"/> ſuche afflyccyons happened vnto hym immediatelye after he had eſtabliſhed the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in hys perſit ordre. For it was verye lykelye,<note place="margin">Whoſo go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth aboute to ſet furth the glorye of GOD, ſhall haue perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> that as ſoone as he went about to ſet foorthe the glorye of God, he ſhoulde not haue hys realme peaceable. So all faythefull Princes and Gouernours of Countreyes be aduertiſed by thys exaumple, that the more they ſhall employe theyr la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to put out all Idolatrye and procure that god be true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wurſhypped (as he ought) the more theyr fayth ſhall bee proued,<note place="margin">Why God ſuffereth godly Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces to bee tempted.</note> by dyuers temptaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. God ſuffereth it, and ſo will haue it, to declare the conſtancie of hys, and to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe
<pb facs="tcp:18766:9"/> them, that they ſhoulde haue regarde to an hygher thyng, then thys worlde.<note place="margin">The deuil laboureth priuely to deſtroy al godly doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note> In the meane tyme the deuil alſo doth hys offyce, entending by al couert and hidden meanes to deſtroye the good doctrine, becauſe he cannot openlye at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to hys deſyre. But folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the admonicion of ſaint Iames (who ſayeth vnto vs: that in conſideryng the paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Iob, we muſte take hede to thende,) we muſt alſo caſte oure eyes vpon the end, whiche was geuen to the ſayde good kynge.<note place="margin">The good ende that GOD ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to the godly.</note> As god ſuccoured hym in all hys ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities, ſo in thende he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned victorious. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng that, and for aſmuch as
<pb facs="tcp:18766:10"/> hys ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is not now any ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than it was than, and that he hath at this day in ſo gret recommendacion the defence of his people, truth and veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as euer he had: Doubte ye not, but that he wil helpe you, and not onelye for one tyme, but in as many temptacions as he ſhall ſend vnto you. If the moſte parte of the worlde reſiſte the Goſpell, and lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe enforceth themſelues, with all rage and violence, to empeache and hyndre the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng furth therof:<note place="margin">The ingra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tytude of men doeth euer more reſiſt God approchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vnto them</note> We ought not to thynke it ſtraunge. For it is the vnthankefulneſſe of menne, which euer haue bene and ſhalbe, to recoyle when GOD approcheth to them,
<pb facs="tcp:18766:10"/> and alſo to ſtumble agaynſte hym, when he will charge them with hys yoke. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, for that of theyr nature they bee geuen to hipocriſie, they maye not endure to bee brought to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woord of GOD, whiche diſcouereth their infamye and ſhame, nor to be drawen out of the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which ſerueth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as hyding places, for to geue them ſhadowe. It is then no new thing, if there bee greate contradiccion, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one goeth aboute to brynge them to the pure obedyence of GOD.<note place="margin">Ieſus bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the ſwerd with the goſpel</note> And alſo we haue aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of oure Lorde Ieſus, the whiche ſayeth to vs, that he hathe brought the ſweorde
<pb facs="tcp:18766:11"/> with his euangelye. But this muſte not aſtonyſhe vs, nor make vs wurſe willynge or fearefull: for in thende when men ſhall haue well mutined and put furth all theyr mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they ſhalbe confounded in a momente, and ſhal ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw themſelues, with theyr owne violences. It is true (as it is ſayde in the ſeconde pſalme) that god ſhall not but laughe at theyr ſtyrrynges,<note place="margin">Howe god laugheth at the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious ſtir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecutours.</note> that is to ſay, that in diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng he ſhall leaue them tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, as the thyng touched hym not. But for all that, in thende they ſhalbe alwayes drieuen backe by hys power, of the whiche if we be armed, we haue a good perfite and
<pb facs="tcp:18766:11"/> inuincible municion againſte all conſpiracies, whatſoeuer the Deuilles maye procure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs. And in thende we ſhall knowe by experyence,<note place="margin">The Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell that maketh a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene god and vs, can alſo a peaſe men</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as the goſpel is the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of peace, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acyon betwene God and vs: So can he aſwel for vs paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye men. And by thys meane, we ſhall feele that Eſai hath not ſayd in vayne, that when Ieſu Chriſte ſhall reygne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges vs by hys doctrine, the ſweordes ſhall be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into plough ſhares, and the ſpeares into Sythes. In the meane tyme, albeit that the malice and Rebellion of men are the occaſion of ſedici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and mewtenies, which ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:18766:12"/> agaynſte the Goſpell: Yet neuertheleſſe it behoueth vs to take hede to our ſelues,<note place="margin">God ſome time chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth vs by the euil perſoues.</note> and to knowe that god chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth oure faultes by them, which otherwiſe cannot ſerue but to Sathan. It hath bene an auncient complaynte, that the Ghoſpell was the cauſe of all euilles and calamities,<note place="margin">Some lay the faulte of ſedicion to the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</note> whiche happened vnto men. In deede we ſee by the hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories that not longe after the chriſtianitie was ſpredde in all places, there was not almoſt a corner in the worlde whiche was not horriblye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flycted. The mocyon of the warres was as an vniuerſal fyer lyghtened in all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes. The floudes in thone
<pb facs="tcp:18766:12"/> ſyde, the Peſtilence and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne in the other, an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible confuſyon of ordre and pollicye, in manner that it was lykelye that the worlde ſhoulde bee clearelye ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned. We haue alſo ſeene in oure tyme, ſythe the goſpel hathe begonne to be abroade, manye myſeryes: So that euerye manne complayneth that we bee in an vnhappye worlde, and there is verye fewe that feeleth not the wayghte of the burden.</p>
            <p>Nowe in feelynge ſuche blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, wee oughte to regarde the hande of hym that ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs, and we oughte alſo to thinke wherfore.<note place="margin">The cauſe why we fele gods ſcourge.</note> The cauſe whiche moueth hym to make
<pb facs="tcp:18766:13"/> vs ſo to feele hys ſcourge, is not very darke or hard to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande. We know that his woorde, by the which he will kepe vs in health, is an ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable treaſure, and in what maner of recompence is it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of vs. Wherfore then, ſeeyng we eſteme not muche that, whiche is ſo precious to ſpeake of: it is reaſon that he take vengeance of our ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. We alſo heare that Ieſus Chriſte ſayde, that the ſeruaunte knowyng the will of hys maiſter and dooyng it not, is worthy of double chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſemente, for becauſe that we bee ſo ſlothfull to obey the wil of oure God, whiche hath bene declared vnto vs, more
<pb facs="tcp:18766:13"/> than an hundred tymes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, we ought not to think it ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, if he be more ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly angrye with vs, ſeing that we be more inexcuſable. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we cauſe not the good ſeede to increaſe and profite: it is reaſon that the thyſtles and thornes of Sathan groweth to prycke and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that we geue not to our creatour the obedience that is due vnto hym: it is no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle that men aryſe agaynſt vs. As I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (my lord) you haue had two kyndes of mutenies, whiche bee riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the king &amp; the ſtate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Realme.<note place="margin">Two kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenies at once.</note> Thone be fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call men, which vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the goſpell, would put
<pb facs="tcp:18766:14"/> all to confuſyon. The other bee obſtynate people in the Superſticyons of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte of Rome. Altogether deſerueth wel to be punyſhed by the ſweorde, that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted vnto you. Seeynge that they quarell, not onelye agaynſte the kynge, but alſo agaynſte God, whiche hathe placed hym in the ſeate Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and hath committed vnto you, the proteccion, aſwell of hys perſon, as of hys maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and regall eſtate.<note place="margin">How gods word muſt be receued</note> But the principal meane is, to doe as much as is poſſible, to cauſe that they which ſauor the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the goſpel (to thintent to ſtycke and cleaue vnto it) ſhoulde receyue it with ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:18766:14"/> humbleneſſe and feare, that they may forſake themſelues for the ſeruice of god. For they ought to thinke that god wil reuele all, to thentente y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall profit more (without fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in his woorde) then they haue done before. Theſe mad folkes that would the worlde ſhould returne into a confuſe &amp; diſordinate libertie, be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned by Sathan for to ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre the goſpel: As y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhould not engendre, but rebellion a gaynſte prynces, and all dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordre emonges the people. Wherfore al faythfull ought to be ſorowful. The Papiſtes willi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to maintain y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> filthy ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of their Romain Idole, ſhew themſelues open
<pb facs="tcp:18766:15"/> enemyes of the grace of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte and of all hys or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunces, the ſame alſo ought to greeue the heartes of al them, whiche haue good zeale, wherfore they ought to thynke altogether that theſe be ſcourges of god, which he ſendeth to them: And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? But onely becauſe that they make none accoumpte of the doctrine of healthe as they ought to doe.<note place="margin">The prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie to appeace ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicion.</note> Wherfore the principall remedye for to appeace ſuch ſedicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is, that they which profeſſeth the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, doe truely repayre to the Image of God, for to ſhewe that our chriſtianitie cauſeth not diſſipacion in the humain lyfe, and geue good proofe &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:18766:15"/> tryall by theyr ſobrenes, and temperaunce, that we gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the woord of God, bee not me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnruled and without a brydle. And by theyr good &amp; holy lyfe, ſtop the mouthes of all euyll ſpeakers. For by thys meanes god (beeing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaced) ſhal retiere hys hand, and in the place that thys day he puniſheth the ſlaunderers, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contemning of his word, he ſhall bleſſe theyr obedience in all proſperitie.<note place="margin">Lawe es &amp; Iuſtices oughte to bee vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt.</note> Lykewyſe that al the nobilitie and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iers gouerne them ſelues ryghtlye, and in all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to thobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this great kyng Ieſus Chriſt: Makyng holy homage vnto him (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feining) of ſoule and body
<pb facs="tcp:18766:16"/> and all that they haue. To thintente, that he correct and abate that to gancie and folly of them, that woulde tyſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them. Loe, thys is the meane howe Princes of the earth ought to reygne in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Ieſus Chriſt, to thende that he may haue Soueraine auctoritie emonges all, bothe great and ſmall. Wherefore my Lorde, in aſmuche as you haue the regall eſtate of the king your Nephieu deare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and in greate recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendacion (as you ſhewe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wel) I pray you in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of god, to employe your prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall care &amp; vigilancye, that the doctrine of God may bee preached with ſtrengthe, and
<pb facs="tcp:18766:16"/> vertue, for to brynge furthe hys fruite, and not to leaue for any reſpecte to purſue a ful and an entiere reformaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Churche. And the better to declare vnto you my mynde and intencion, I will deuyde the whole into three poyntes. The fyrſt ſhalbe the meane to inſtructe the people well.<note place="margin">The reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte all ſedicion in a common weale.</note> The ſeconde ſhalbe the taking away of the abuſe that hath bene of longe tyme. The third with dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to correct vyces, and to kepe ſo good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre that the ſlaundres &amp; diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres may not haue ſuch place as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the name of God ſhoulde bee blaſphemed. As to the fyrſte I mynde not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto you what doctrine
<pb facs="tcp:18766:17"/> ought to haue place. But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I geue thankes to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty god, that beſides that he hathe geuen vnto you the light of his pure knowledge, he hath alſo geuen vnto you, good counſell and diſcrecion, to cauſe hys pure veritie to be preached. So that God be thanked, you be not to teache what is the true faith of chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the doctrine that they ought to receiue. Seing that by youre meane, the true puretie of the faythe is reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. That is, that we belieue and take God for the onelye gouerner of oure ſoules: that we kepe hys lawe for the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rule, and ſpiritual gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of oure conſcience, and
<pb facs="tcp:18766:17"/> not to ſerue him after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fooliſh inuencyon of man. Alſo, that accordyng to hys nature, he wilbe ſerued in ſpirite, and in puritie of heart. Of the other parte, knowyng that there is not but al euil in vs, and that we bee corrupted in all oure knowledge and affeccyons, on that ſorte, that our ſoules being deſpayred in our ſelfes be lyke a bottomles pytte, or worlde of iniquitie. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken away al preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of our wiſedome, dygni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or power to dooe well: we may haue recourſe to the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of al goodnes, which is Ieſus Chriſt, receiuyng that which he geueth vs: that is to ſaye, the merite of hys deathe
<pb facs="tcp:18766:18"/> and paſſion. To thintout that by that meane we may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God, that beeyng waſhed with hys bloude, we ſhoulde not feare that oure faultes ſhoulde empeache or hyndre vs, to fynde grace before hys celeſtiall throne. That beyng certain that ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſynnes be frely pardoned vs, by vertue of hys ſacrifice, we ſhal put therin our truſt &amp; aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, for to be aſſerteyned of our healthe, and that we bee ſanctifyed by his ſprite, in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge our ſelues to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the iuſtice of GOD, that beeynge fortifyed by hys grace, we ſhalbe vanquiſhers of Sathan, the worlde, and the fleſhe. Finally, that being
<pb facs="tcp:18766:18"/> membres of hys bodye, we feare it not, but GOD will take vs for hys children, and that wee maye haue confy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to call vnto hym as oure father. That we be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertyſed to brynge to thys ende, al that is ſayd and done in the church, it is, that beyng retiered from the worlde, wee maye bee lyfte vp to heauen, with our head and Sauior. Wherefore ſeeyng than that god hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you the grace to reſtore the knowledge of hys doctrine, whiche hathe beene ſo longe buryed by the Antichriſte, I leaue to kepe you with longer purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And that whiche I haue towched of the manner of
<pb facs="tcp:18766:19"/> teaching, is onely for that the people maye bee ryghtlye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and for to feele that which thapoſtle ſayd:<note place="margin">The word of God is a two ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſword</note> that is, that the woorde of God is a ſweorde, cutting with two ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, pearſyng the thoughtes and affeccions vnto the mary of the bone.<note place="margin">Few god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinges in the realm</note> I ſaye thys (my Lord) for that I thynke there is veraye fewe lyuelye prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynges within the realme. But that the moſt parte recy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, as by lecture, I well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the neceſſytye that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayneth you thereunto. For fyrſte you haue not (as I think) your paſtours ſo good and apt, as you deſire &amp; wiſhe, wherfore it is nedeful for you to ſupply that lack. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:18766:19"/> there myght chaunce to bee manye lighte ſpirites, whiche woulde peraduenture leape beyond theyr bondes, ſowing ſome foolyſhe fantaſyes, as many tymes they doe in newe thynges. But all theſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracyons empeacheth not,<note place="margin">The ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of Ieſus Chriſto oughte in al cauſes to haue courſe.</note> but that thordinaunce of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte ought to haue his courſe as in preachynge the goſpel. Nowe ths preachyng oughte not to bee dead but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyue,<note place="margin">Prechyng oughte to be liuely.</note> for to teache exhorte and reprehende (as Saint Paule ſayth to Timoth:) yea in ſuch ſorte as if an infidele entre, he may bee wounded ouercome, and taken (as the ſame Paul ſayeth in another place,) for to geue glory vnto god. You
<pb facs="tcp:18766:20"/> knowe alſo, my Lorde, howe as he ſpeaketh of the lyueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that oughte to bee in the mouthes of them, which will approue them ſelues good and faythfull miniſters of the goſpell, that they ought not to haue or vſe woordes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorike, entending thereby to be in greater eſtimacyon: but that the ſpirite of God ought to ſounde in theyr voyces, for to woorke in dertue. All the daungers that are to bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ought not to impeache the ſpirite of God to haue hys li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and his courſe, in them in the which he hath diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of hys grace, for to edifye the churche. It is true that in the meane time it is good and
<pb facs="tcp:18766:20"/> expedient to ſtop the lightnes of fantaſtical ſpirites, that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to muche lycence. Alſo to ſhut the gate of al curioſities and newe fangled doctrines. But the beſt and moſt conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient meanes, ſuche as God hath ſhewed vnto vs, is,<note place="margin">There ought to be a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of doctrin that ſhould bee preached.</note> that firſt there bee a ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me reſolute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine that al ought to preache, the which al prelates and curates ſhould ſweare to folowe: And that none bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued to anye eccleſiaſticall charge,<note place="margin">All prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers oughte to preache v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformly.</note> but he promyſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the ſame concorde and vnpon.<note place="margin">cathechiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes for the youth oughte to be had in a chriſten realme.</note> After that to haue a formall and commen inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon for to enſtructe the younge chyldren and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunte people, whyche ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:18766:21"/> make them acquaynted with the true doctrine, in ſuch wyſe that they may diſcerne it from lyes and corrupcions, whiche elles myght be broughte in. To the contrarye, belieue my lorde, that the churche of god ſhal neuer be conſerued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Cathechiſme: for it is as the ſeede, to bee kept, that the good grayne peryſhe not, but that it may encreaſe from age to age. Wherfore if you deſire to builde a worke of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce to endure long, &amp; which ſhoulde not ſhortly fall in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, cauſe that the children in theyr yong age, be enſtructed with a good Cathechiſme, that may learne them briefly, and according to theyr ſmall
<pb facs="tcp:18766:21"/> capacities, to knowe wherein conſyſteth the true chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. <note place="margin">The profi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tableneſſe of a good cathechiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</note> Thys<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cathechiſme ſhall ſerue for two purpoſes, that is to ſay, for an introduccyon to al the people, for to profite wel in that which ſhalbe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto them, and alſo to diſcerne in caſe any preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly would attempt to ſet furth ſtraunge doctrines. In the meane time I ſay not,<note place="margin">It is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarye to bynde the Paſtour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain forme of doctrine written.</note> and alſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to bynde and reſtrayn the paſtoures and Curates to a certain forme written, for to ſupplye the ignorauncies and ſymplenes of ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and alſo the better to ſhewe the conformitie and concorde of all churches. Thyrdelye,
<pb facs="tcp:18766:22"/> for to brydle all curioſityes and newe inuencions, ſuche as deſyres nothynge, but to runne ryot, the ſayde Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, (as I haue before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed) ſhall ſerue and bees good brydle for ſuche folkes: And alſo in ſuch ſorte ordre is to be geuen, in the miniſtring of the Sacramentes, and in the publike prayers. But in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane tyme,<note place="margin">The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chinge the Ghoſpell may not be deſtroyed</note> you muſt take heede that ſuche pollicie deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troy not the ſtrength and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue that oughte to be in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the goſpel. And that you employe youre labour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſmuche as ye poſſiblye can, that there bee good trumpets whiche maye enter into the depenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hertes, for ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:18766:22"/> is daunger that ye ſhall not ſee greate profite of ſuche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cion,<note place="margin">Good pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g muſt be ioyned with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formacion</note> how good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſoeuer it bee, vnleſſe that euen at once with it, the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and vertue of good prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, bee deſplayed and ſette foorthe togethers. It is not without<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſe that it is ſayd that Ieſus Chriſt ſhall ſtrike the year<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he by the Sceptre of hys mouthe, and ſhall deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troye the euyll by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of hys lyppes. It is the meane by the whiche he will ouercome vs, in deſtroyinge all that, whiche is agaynſte hym.<note place="margin">The goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is in ſcripture called the kingdome of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> And for that cauſe the goſpel is alſo called the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of GOD. Alſo, albeit that thordinances &amp; ſtatutes
<pb facs="tcp:18766:23"/> of princes bee good helpes to aduaunce and mayntaine the ſtate of chriſtianitie: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe god will declare hys ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereygne vertue in the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſweorde of hys woorde with it, ſetting furth theſame by his paſtours. And to thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent I woulde not long trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you (my Lord) I wil come to the ſeconde poynt which I haue purpoſed to ſhewe vnto you.<note place="margin">Abuſes muſte bee cleane ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away</note> It is to abolyſhe, and clearely to take away, the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſes &amp; corrupcions that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than hath mingled heretofore with the ordinaunces of god. We knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnder the pope there is a baſtard chriſtianitie whiche god ſhall dyſalowe in the laſte daye:<note place="margin">Vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> papacie is a baſtarde chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> foraſmuche as
<pb facs="tcp:18766:23"/> at thys daye, he hath condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſame, by hys woorde. If wee deſyre to retiere the worlde from ſuche perdicion, there is nothyng better, then to folow the exaumple of. S. Paule, who willynge to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte the euyll that the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians had ioyned to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of our Lorde, ſayde vnto them: I haue receyued of the Lord, that whiche I haue ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto you.<note place="margin">We mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> returne to the ryght commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement of GOD.</note> Of that we muſt gather one generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruccion to returne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right and natural commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God: if we wil haue a good and an approued reformacion of hym. For ſo manye myng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges as men haue ſet vp of theyr owne inuencions, there
<pb facs="tcp:18766:24"/> be ſo many infecctons, which turne vs from the holy vſage of that, that God hath geuen vs, for our healthe. So to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of halfe the braunches of ſuch abuſes,<note place="margin">It is not enough to cut of ſum of the bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſes.</note> it cannot bring again the thynges in perfecte and pure ſtate, beecauſe that wee then ſhall haue alwayes a Chriſtianitie counterfette. I ſay thys for that, that ſome vnder the coulour of modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, bee of opinion to ſuffre many abuſes, without taking them awaye, and they thynke that it is inough to haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out the roote of the principal. But contrary wiſe, we ſe how muche the ſeede of lyes is fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile,<note place="margin">The ſeede of lyes is fertile.</note> and that one grayne of that is ſufficiente, for to fyll
<pb facs="tcp:18766:24"/> all the worlde within three dayes, as menne bee enclined and geuen vnto. Our Lorde teacheth vs otherwyſe, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dauid ſpeaketh of idols he ſayeth that their name ſhal not paſſe by hys mouthe: to thentente to declare vnto vs what horror and deteſtacion wee oughte to haue them in. And if we conſidre well how much we haue offended God in the time of our ignoraunce, we ought to be dowbly reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred for to eſchew the inuenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Sathan,<note place="margin">The craft of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> who hathe prouoked vs to doe ſuch euil thinges, vſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes whiche ſerueth not, but to ſeduce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore &amp; ſimple folkes. On the other ſyde we
<pb facs="tcp:18766:25"/> ſee that albeit menne be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly warned of their faultes, and errours, and be aduerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of them aſmuch as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: Yet neuertheles, they be ſo hardened, that no man can attayne to the perfecte ende. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if there ſhalbe left vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome dregges to remaine, it ſhalbe a nouryſhemente of muche more and greater ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacye, and a couerture to hyde all doctrine that may be propouned vnto them. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that it is conueniente to obſerue ſome moderacyon,<note place="margin">Moderaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarye, and ſome cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies may be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> and that to great extremitie is neither good ne profitable. Lykewyſe it is conuenient to vſe the ceremonies according to the groſenes of the people:
<pb facs="tcp:18766:25"/> but it maye not bee that that whiche is of Sathan, and of the Antichriſte, ſhoulde paſſe vnder that coloure. It is for that cauſe that holye ſcripture praiſing the kinges which did deſtroy the idolatries,<note place="margin">The kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that deſtroyed Idolatrie.</note> not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g plucked away altogether: neuertheles gaue vnto them a marke for that they had not deſtroyed the chappelles and places of foolyſhe deuocion. Wherfore my lord, ſeing that god hath brought you ſo farre foorth, I praye you continue without any excepcion, to the intente that he maye approue you the ſetter foorthe of hys temple: in ſuche wyſe as the tyme of the kynge youre Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phieu maye bee compared to
<pb facs="tcp:18766:26"/> the time of Ioſias: and that you maye ſette al thynges in ſuche ſtate as there ſhall reſte nothyng to hym, but to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the good ordre whiche god ſhal haue prepared vnto hym by your meane. I wil al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege vnto you an exaumple of ſuche dregges, whiche perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture may reſt to bee a litle leuen: the which in thend, will make the paſte ſowre.<note place="margin">Agaynſte prayinge for the dead at re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</note> They dooe in your countreye ſome kynde of prayer for the dead, when the communion is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued. I know wel it is not for to aduowe the purgatory of the Pope. I know alſo that it maye be alleged by aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente cuſtome to dooe ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce for the dead, to
<pb facs="tcp:18766:26"/> the intente to ioyne together all the membres of the bodye. But there is a peremptorye argumente to the contrarye, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt is ſo holye a thynge, that it ought not to bee defyled with no inuencions of men. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, that in praying vnto god, we ought not lette ſlippe the brydle of our fantaſticall deuocion, but to kepe the rule that Saincte Paule did geue vnto vs: that is, that we take our foundacion of the woord of god. Wherfore ſuch reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of recommendacion is not conuenient to the ordre of the good and due prayer, and it is an euyll addicyon to the holy ſupper of our Lorde.
<pb facs="tcp:18766:27"/> There is other thynges, whiche peraduenture ſhould be leſſe blamed, whiche neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles, is not to bee excuſed: As y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ceremony of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chreame and vnccion.<note place="margin">The cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of chreame &amp; vnccion.</note> The chreame hath bene inuented of a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe fantaſye by them that contented not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with the adminiſtracion of Ieſus Chriſte, and that they would counterfet the holy ſpirite by a new doctrine, as though the water were not ſufficiente e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for that. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is called the extreme vnccion, hath bene retayned by a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe affeccyon of them, that haue will to folow the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, hauing not the ſame gift that they hadde. For when the
<pb facs="tcp:18766:27"/> Apoſtles dyd vſe the oyle vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſyck,<note place="margin">The oile vſed vpon the ſycke by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</note> it was for to heale them by miracle: when the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle ceaſſed, the figure ought no more to be vſed.<note place="margin">Superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cerem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies are to be pared of agayne.</note> Wherfore it ſhould be a great deale bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the thynges ſhoulde be ſo pared of agayn, as they may be moſt agreeing to the pure woorde of God, and may ſerue to the edifyinge of the church.<note place="margin">Howe wee oughte to beare with the weake.</note> It is true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ought to beare with the weake, but that is for to ſtrengthen and bryng them to greater perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, that is not to ſay that in the meane tyme we ought to pleaſe fooles whiche deſyre now this &amp; now that, &amp; know not wherefore. I knowe the conſideracyon wherefore ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:18766:28"/> are troubled: it is that they feare that to much alteracion cannot bee borne with, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pallye when one will haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of hys neyghboures, with whome he deſyreth to nouriſhe frendſhip and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. A man would gladly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifye them in dyſſymulynge many thynges. Thys oughte to bee borne with, in worldly affayres, where it is lawefull to yelde one to an other, and to geue ſome of our ryghte to bye peace: but it is not al one of the ſpirituall gouernaunce of the Churche,<note place="margin">As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g gods woord, we maye not yelde to menne for fauout.</note> the whiche oughte to bee ordred accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the woorde of God. In that it is not in oure ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye to yelde in anye thyng
<pb facs="tcp:18766:28"/> to menne, in reſpecte of theyr fauoure. Lykewyſe there is nothynge that dyſpleaſeth GOD more, then when we will by oure humayne pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, moderate or temper, or refourme, or ſette foorthe, or drawe backe, anye thynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte hys wyll. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if wee will not dyſpleaſe hym, wee muſte cloſe oure eyes in reſpecte of menne. As to the daungers that maye happen, wee oughte to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewe them as muche as we maye: but not in declynynge from the trewe and ryghte waye, for wee haue hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe,<note place="margin">God by his promiſe will aſſiſte vs in wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge the right way.</note> that he wyll aſſyſte vs in walking the right way.
<pb facs="tcp:18766:29"/> So that it reſteth not in vs, but to doe our office in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendynge to hym that,<note place="margin">Why the wyſe of this world are manye tymes vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yd of their hope.</note> that ſhall folowe. And for that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion the wyſe of thys world be many tymes voyde of their hope, for that, that god is not with them, when they truſte not in hym, and in hys helpe in ſerching bymeanes, which he condemneth. If then wee wil haue the vertue &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of god on oure ſyde, let vs fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe ſymplye, that he ſayeth vnto vs, and aboue all, wee oughte to kepe thys generall rule:<note place="margin">The refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macyon of the church is the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of gods owne hand</note> that the reformacion of hys churche is the woorke of hys hande. Wherfore it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye, that in thys matter, men ſuffre themſelues to bee
<pb facs="tcp:18766:29"/> gouerned by hym, the whiche whether it bee in reſtoryng or in kepynge hys churche, will moſt commonly procede by a merueylouſe and ſtraunge meanes and wayes, vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to menne. Wherefore to reſtrayne thys reformacyon that ought to bee diuyne, by the meaſure of our witte, and to make that whiche is celeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall ſubiecte to the earth and the world, is agaynſt al good reaſon. By that I exclude not the wiſedome whiche is very requiſite to obſerue all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice and good meanes, and not to excede eyther on thone ſyde or thother, in any extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, for the wynnyng of all the worlde to god, if it ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:18766:30"/> be poſſible.<note place="margin">It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that the wiſedome of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite rule, and not of the fleſhe.</note> But it is nedefull that the wiſedome of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite ſhoulde rule, and not of the fleſhe. And that hauyng examined the mouthe of the Lorde, wee require of hym, that he will be our guyde and conducter, ſoner the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to folowe oure owne wittes: and when we ſhal require it in that ſort, it ſhalbee eaſye for vs to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude many temptacions, that maye ſtaye vs in the middes of the waye. Wherefore my Lorde, as you haue begonne to reduce Chriſtianitie vnto hys perfect ſtate in England, and not in truſtyng of youre ſelfe, but to bee mayntayned by the hande of GOD: as vnto thys daye ye haue felte
<pb facs="tcp:18766:30"/> hys myghtye hande, doubte ye not, but that he wil helpe you vnto the ende. For if god mayntayneth kyngedomes and Lordeſhyppes of infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels that bee hys enemyes,<note place="margin">If GOD maintaine the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of Infidele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, much m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> he will of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</note> by muche more reaſon, he will take into hys garde, them that bee obedyent vnto hym, and dooe take hym for theyr Superyoure. I come now to the laſte Article, that is, to punyſhe vyce, and to reproue ſlaunders. I doubte not but there is good lawes, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtatutes, wythin the Realme of Englande,<note place="margin">People muſte by good law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es be kept in a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honeſt diſcipline</note> for to keepe the people in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte lyfe. But the greate dyſordres and enormytyes that I ſee in the worlde,
<pb facs="tcp:18766:31"/> conſtraineth me to deſyre you to take alſo the care that the people be kepte in good and honeſt diſciplyne: and aboue all that ye haue the honour of God in good reputacyon, to the intente to punyſhe ſuche crymes,<note place="margin">Crymes muſt be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed.</note> of the whiche menne accuſtomablye make none ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpte. I ſaye it for that, that ſomtymes, theftes, Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beryes, fyghtynges, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torcyons ſhall bee ſharpelye puniſhed, for that in thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be offended: and in the meane time whordomes, adulteries, dronkenes, and blaſphemies of the name of god, be ſuffred almoſte as thynges lawfull and of ſmall importaunce. Contrariwyſe we ſee in what
<pb facs="tcp:18766:31"/> eſtimacyon and deteſtacyon god hathe them in. For he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth vnto vs, howe muche his name is precyouſe, and in what eſtimacion we ought to haue it: and yet it is by vs, as it were torne in pieces, and troden vnder our fete. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of doubte, he wil not leaue vnpuniſhed ſuche iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and dyſhonour. Yea, and moreouer the Scripture ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vs that by blaſphemies a whole realme is infected.<note place="margin">By blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies a whol real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</note> As touching adultries, it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great ſhame vnto vs whiche profeſſe the name of Chriſte, that the Pagans haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued greater rygour in puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng therof then we dooe: of the whiche we manye tymes
<pb facs="tcp:18766:32"/> make but a laughing game. When the holy mariage that ought to bee a lyuelye ymage of the holye vnyon that wee haue with the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">Holy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note> is defyled, and that the ally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce whiche oughte to bee moſt ſtable and indyſſoluble, is vniuſtlye broken: If wee take not thoſe thynges to hearte, it is a ſygne that wee haue no greate care nor loue of GOD. Touching whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, it may well ſuffyce vs that Sayncte Paule doothe compare it to Sacrilege,<note place="margin">S. Paule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pareth whoredom to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege.</note> for aſmuche as by the ſame the temples of GOD, which is our bodyes, bee prophaned and defyled. Item that the whoremongers and dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kardes
<pb facs="tcp:18766:32"/> bee banyſhed from the kyngdome of GOD, in ſuch wyſe that it is defended vnto vs to keepe companye with them. Wherefore it foloweth that they oughte not to bee ſuffered in the Churche.<note place="margin">Whormo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kardes ought not to be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red in the Churche.</note> And thys is the cauſe that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye tribulacyons bee thys daye vpon the yearthe. For inſomuche as menne pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſuche enormities, it muſt folowe that GOD muſt take vengeaunce. Wherefore my lord, to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to preuent his wrath, I pray you to hold the brydle ſhorte, &amp; cauſe that they whiche heareth the doctrine of the Ghoſpell, proue them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues to bee chriſten menne, by the holyneſſe of theyr lyfe.
<pb facs="tcp:18766:33"/> For as the doctrine is the ſoule of the church, for to geue it lyfe: ſo the diſciplyne and correccion of vices bee as the Senowes for to mayntayne the body in his force &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth.<note place="margin">Correccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vyces.</note> It is the office of Buſſhops and Curates to take good hede to the ſame,<note place="margin">The office of biſhops &amp; curates.</note> to the intent that the ſupper of oure Lorde bee not polluted by folkes of ſlaunderous and dyſhoneſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> life. But conſidering the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie whiche God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto you, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principall charge retourneth vnto you, for to ſet others in the ryght waye, to thintent that euerye one dyſcharge themſelues of theyr duetie, and cauſe that the ordre which is eſtabliſhed
<pb facs="tcp:18766:33"/> be duely obſerued. Nowe my Lorde folowing the proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon that I haue made here beefore, I will not excuſe my ſelf no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, neither of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixitie of my letters, nor of that, that I haue liberally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that I had in my hert. For I truſt that myne affecci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowen vnto you, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your wiſdom. And as ye be exerciſed in the holye ſcripture, you ſee of what fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne I haue drawen all that whiche is herein conteyned. Wherefore I dooe not feare that I haue bene tedious and importune in declaryng vnto you, to the beſt of my power, the good deſyre that I haue, that the name of god may be
<pb facs="tcp:18766:34"/> daylye by you more largelye gloryfyed, for the whyche I pray to hym daylye. Praying that it maye pleaſe hym to augment his grace vnto you, confyrmyng you by hys holye ſpirite in a perfect and inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible conſtancie, maintaining you againſt your enemies, ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing you with all your houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde in his holy proteccion, and doing that you adminiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter happelye the charge that is committed to you. So that the kyng may haue occaſion to geue thankes to hys Lord God, for that he hathe hadde ſuche a Gouernoure in hys younge age, aſwell of hys perſon as alſo of hys realme. So I make an ende my lord,
<pb facs="tcp:18766:34"/> hauynge me moſte humblye recommended vnto your good Grace:</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The .xxii. of Octobre, in the yeare of oure LORDE. 1549.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt humble ſeruaunt, John Caluine</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>IMPRINTED AT LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Edward whitchurche, the .v. daye of Aprill. 1550.</p>
            <q>Cum priuilegio, ad Jmprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</q>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
